<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The battaile fovght betvveene Count Maurice of Nassaw, and Albertus arch-duke of Austria, nere Newport in Flaunders, the xxij. of Iune 1600 with the names of such men of accompt as haue beene either slaine, hurt, or taken prisoners by either part. Written by a gentleman imploied in the said seruice.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07276</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17671A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113130</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848369</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848369</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13459</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07276)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13459)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1606:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The battaile fovght betvveene Count Maurice of Nassaw, and Albertus arch-duke of Austria, nere Newport in Flaunders, the xxij. of Iune 1600 with the names of such men of accompt as haue beene either slaine, hurt, or taken prisoners by either part. Written by a gentleman imploied in the said seruice.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 5 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By P. Short] for Andrew Wise,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>B2 torn, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B²  (-A1, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Maurice, --  Prince of Orange, 1567-1625.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:13459:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>MAURITIUS AVR. PRINC. COM. NASS. MURS. <hi>etc.</hi> MARC VERAE ET VLISS CONF. BELG. PROV. GUB.</head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Count Maurice of Nassau</figDesc>
                  <p>Mauritz Prince van Orangien Grave, van Naſsau, Meurs etc Gouverneur generael van<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Geunieede Nederlanden. Ridder der Co van<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fartiere.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13459:1"/>
            <p>THE BATTAILE FOVGHT BETVVEENE Count <hi>Maurice</hi> of Naſſaw, and <hi>Albertus</hi> Arch-duke of Auſtria, nere Newport in Flaunders, the xxij. of Iune 1600, <hi>With the names of ſuch men of accompt</hi> as haue beene either ſlaine, hurt, or <hi>taken priſoners by either</hi> part.</p>
            <p>Written by a Gentleman imploied in the ſaid ſeruice.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>P S</head>
               <q xml:lang="lat">ET VSQVE AD NVBES VERITAS TVA</q>
               <figDesc>printer's device consisting of an open book surrounded by a sunburst and containing a motto; beneath are the initials "P S", indicating that the device originally belonged to the printer Peter Short(1589-1603) but was probably passed on to Andrew Wise (1589-1603) at some point</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London for <hi>Andrew Wiſe,</hi> 1600.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account_of_battle">
            <pb facs="tcp:13459:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13459:2"/>
            <head>¶ The Battaile fought betweene Count <hi>Maurice</hi> of Naſſaw, and <hi>Albertus</hi> Arch-duke of Auſtria.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>IS excellencies</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was to hould, <hi>Oudenborough, Brendike, Snaskirke,</hi> and the new ſconſe vpon the downes nere vnto <hi>Oſtend</hi> called <hi>Albertus,</hi> well garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, the better to aſſure himſelfe of thoſe paſſages whiles hee laide ſiege to <hi>Newport.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond daie of the ſiege being Saterdaie the one and twentieth of <hi>Iune,</hi> intelligence came that the enemie was come to <hi>Oudenborough,</hi> which his excellency ſuppoſed to be <hi>Iohn de Riuas</hi> with the forces of <hi>Flaunders:</hi> but ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after aduertiſement came, that the Archduke was there in perſon and had taken in <hi>Oudenborough</hi> by compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherevpon his excellencie bethought himſelfe, howe he might beſt hinder his nearer approach: And becauſe he feared leaſt in the purſuite, the enemie might take in the ſconſe <hi>Albertus,</hi> and ſo cut off the paſſage betwéene <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> and <hi>Oſtend,</hi> he ſent the Regiment of the <hi>Scots</hi> on the ſundaie morning, and the Regiment of the <hi>Almains</hi> vnder the command of <hi>Count Erneſtus</hi> to hinder the paſſage by a bridge, which was made by vs in a dround land betwéene
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13459:3"/>
               <hi>Oudenborough</hi> and the ſconſe <hi>Albertus,</hi> and ſo he ſhoulde put them to march thrée daies about, before they came vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and then alſo it was in his choiſe, either to fight or leaue them, and returne to <hi>Oſtend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the enemie had paſſed the Bridge before the <hi>Scots</hi> could come to make good the place: and ſo they all fell vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the execution of the vangard of the enemie, being all Spaniards, and the choiſeſt men of the Armie: and were chaſed to the wals of <hi>Oſtend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His excellencie vnderſtanding that the enemie was come to the bridge, but not knowing of the execution which he had made of the <hi>Scots,</hi> cauſed the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and the <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> to be drawne at a low water, from the other ſide of the Hauen of <hi>Newport,</hi> where they were quartered before the Towne, and ſo brought all his forces to an head: at what time it was diſputed, whether they ſhoulde ſende forth the troupes as they paſſed ouer the water, to ſecond the <hi>Scots;</hi> or kéepe themſelues together, till further aduertiſement, which was the ſafer courſe; and by good happe reſolued vppon.</p>
            <p>Preſentlie vppon this reſolution, part of the enemies Horſe, being about ſeauen hundred, began to be diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon the ſands as they came on marching forward, and their foote Troupes following after.</p>
            <p>Count <hi>Lodwick</hi> beeing generall of the Horſe, at his excellencies commaunde, gaue ouer the whole direction thereof, to Sir <hi>Francis Vere,</hi> who firſt commanded ſix pée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Artillerie, which were planted vpon the enemie, to be diſcharged vpon the enemies Horſe, and then charged them himſelfe with thrée troupes of Horſe, and beate them into the Downes: the <hi>Infanterie</hi> of the enemie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſtand vpon the ſands.</p>
            <p>The enemies Horſe beeing thus driuen into the Downes, the commanders entred into diſpute, whether it were beſt to aduaunce forwarde and charge vppon their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13459:3"/>foote troupes, as they ſtood vppon the ſandes; or to kéepe our ſelues in the Downes, where we ſtoode imbattailed, and there attend the enemie: wherein ſir <hi>Francis Vere</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed himſelfe againſt the whole counſell of warre, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding himſelfe vpon theſe reaſons: that it was not ſafe to leaue a place of aduantage, to goe ſeeke an enemie vpon equall tearmes, conſidering the enemie would bee forced himſelfe to ſéeke battell, and come vnto vs: for it was vnpoſſible in that haſtie March, which paſſed all calculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of reaſon, that they ſhould ſo come prouided with neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, to continue anie time, whereas our men were vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled for two daies, and ſhoulde in that time méete with ſome alteration.</p>
            <p>The reſolution was directed by his opinion, and his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie continued firme in the Downes to ſee what the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimie would doe.</p>
            <p>It fell out according vnto that, that Syr <hi>Francis Vere</hi> had before deliuered: for after thrée houres expectation, the enemie came on to charge the Engliſh, which had the Vaungard of our Armie.</p>
            <p>The Engliſh as I ſaide, being the Vaungard, hauing ioined battell within a ſhort time, forced the enemie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat: Who flying to the toppes of the Downes, as our Engliſh followed the purſuit, it happened (as neceſſarilie it muſt thorough the vneuenneſſe of the place, which was vncaple of order, being nothing but hilles and valleies of ſand) that the enemie had the like aduantage of our men, as ours had before vpon them: ſo that our men ſometime fell off from the enemie, and ſometime the enemie fell off from them, as the aduantage of the place aſſiſted either partie: which continued the ſpace of thrée houres and an halfe. In which time, the Engliſh dealt with the vaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, the battell and rereward of the enimy: at length the engliſh were beaten backe to our Artillerie, where Sir
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13459:4"/>
               <hi>Francis Vere</hi> brought them againe to a ſtande, and beeing himſelfe hurt, gaue order for the charge the ſeconde time, and commanded the following thereof to his brother Syr <hi>Horatio Vere,</hi> who carried it ſo well, that concerning the fortune of the daie, there is much attributed to his val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. For our Troupes charging the enemie with a ſhout, and being ſeconded with two Troupes of Horſe, after the battell was well ioyned, the enemie diſrowted and neuer made head againe.</p>
            <p>It appeareth that all our Engliſh that were loſt, were ſlaine betweene our Canon and the Canon of the enemie, which were planted in the front of either Armie.</p>
            <p>The Arch-duke had intelligence that the ſtates were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene ſeauen or eight thouſand ſtrong on foote, and foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téene companies of Horſe.</p>
            <p>The Arch-duke came with reſolution to fight in what place ſoeuer he found the ſtates forces, in regard he knew of what conſequent it was, to ſuffer them to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſtrong in <hi>Flaunders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Lewis de Valaſco,</hi> generall of the Arch-dukes Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillerie came from <hi>Gilders</hi> and <hi>Berk</hi> vpon the <hi>Rheine</hi> with certaine companies, being three thouſande: all the reſt of the commanders came from <hi>Bruxels,</hi> and the Rendeuous was at <hi>Bruges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſabella</hi> the <hi>Infanta</hi> was left at <hi>Gaunt,</hi> ſhee came from <hi>Bruxels</hi> with the Arch-duke.</p>
            <p>The Arch-duke came out of <hi>Bruxels</hi> vpon Thurſday the nineteenth of Iune, <hi>Stilo noſtro,</hi> being the ſame day that the Sconſe called <hi>Albertus,</hi> diſtant from <hi>Oſtend</hi> vpon the Downes, an engliſh myle, was taken in by his excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, our Troupes being all at <hi>Oudenborough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Arch-duke made ſuch haſt to ouertake our troupes, that as <hi>Lewis de Villar</hi> confeſſeth, the commaunders had no leiſure to take notice what Gentlemen of ſtate were in the Armie: ſo that they came to <hi>Oudenborough</hi> vppon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13459:4"/>Saturdaie the twentie one of Iune, and fought vpon ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the twentie two.</p>
            <p>Aſſoone as the Arch-duke had intelligence of the Army, arriued at <hi>Phillippine,</hi> hee ſent to <hi>Don Lewis de Valaſco</hi> to bring the men from <hi>Berk,</hi> and diſpoſed the reſt of the troups to méete with the ſaid <hi>Don Lewis</hi> at <hi>Bruges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt ſquadron of the enemies were all Spaniards, conſiſting of <hi>2500.</hi> men, and commanded by
<list>
                  <item>Iaſper Sapena,</item>
                  <item>Don Ieronimo de Morkoy, and</item>
                  <item>Lewis de Villar.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond ſquadron were all <hi>Wallons,</hi> equall in number to the firſt, and commanded by
<list>
                  <item>La Berlot,</item>
                  <item>Don Alphonſo de Auo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, &amp; Boſtock the nephew of Sir Will, Stanley.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The third ſquadron were all of <hi>Flaunders</hi> and of like number with the firſt, commanded by <hi>Le Count de Bonckoper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Admyrant of <hi>Arragon</hi> was generall of the horſe conſiſting of <hi>1000.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>William Stanley</hi> attended the Arch-duke without command, hauing ſigned his Regiment to his Nephew <hi>Boſtocke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> had the Vauntgard, the <hi>French</hi> the Battaile.</p>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:13459:5"/>
               <head>Captaines of the Engliſh Slaine.</head>
               <item>1 Captaine Yaxley,</item>
               <item>2 Captaine Honywood,</item>
               <item>3 Captaine Duxbery,</item>
               <item>4 Captaine Purton,</item>
               <item>5 Captaine Tirrell,</item>
               <item>6 Captaine Woodward.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Lieutenants Slaine.</head>
               <item>Pierce D. Vere, Lieu.</item>
               <item>Read: Morgan, Lieu.</item>
               <item>Mallery Tirrell, Lieu.</item>
               <item>Scot. Honywood, Lieu.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Captaines hurt.</head>
               <item>Hamond</item>
               <item>Holcroft</item>
               <item>Daniell Vere</item>
               <item>Vauyſor</item>
               <item>Morgan</item>
               <item>Scotte</item>
               <item>Fearefax</item>
               <item>Petfield</item>
               <item>Metkerke</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Ancients Slaine.</head>
               <item>Sherman, Yax</item>
               <item>Helues Garnets</item>
               <item>More of ours Slaine and miſſing, 560.</item>
               <item>Men hurt, 250.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:13459:5"/>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </head>
               <item>Drury</item>
               <item>Roceſter</item>
               <item>Gilbert</item>
               <item>Grey</item>
               <item>Voſie</item>
               <item>More</item>
               <item>Kendall</item>
               <item>Wray</item>
               <item>Legge</item>
               <item>Bethro</item>
               <item>Fludde</item>
               <item>Audlin</item>
               <item>Fitz Edmunds</item>
               <item>Dudley</item>
               <item>Kempe</item>
               <item>Cooke</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>taken</hi> 110.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <head>Priſoners of theirs <hi>taken, viz.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>The Admirant of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon.</item>
                  <item>Lewis de Villar, and</item>
                  <item>Iaſper Sapena,</item>
               </list> With many other Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and Gentlemen of ſort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our forces were</hi> 11000. <hi>horſe and foote: That tranſported them</hi> 1128. <hi>ſale beſides men of warre.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
